[Music]
brett thank you very much for joining me
thanks for having me so we're going to
talk about the unity 2020
plan uh which maybe some people watching
this will have already been aware of
but i want to do it from a perspective
that viewers of
rebel wisdom and probably viewers of
your podcast will be familiar with which
is this idea of the game b
and game a dynamic game a being
the current system and there's all sorts
of game theoretic traps there are there
are traps
for example the race to the bottom uh
the tragedy of the commons
you've outlined that a lot in a lot of
your previous work
and there's a group of people uh that
have been looking at
society through that framework and
saying okay the entire source code
of this game a structure is
self-terminating in many ways
and you can look at the choices that
have been presented in the 2020 election
as evidence of
this system becoming more and more
dysfunctional
and then game b is a placeholder for a
different system like there's all sorts
of game b
projects and they the
the main features they have is that they
deal with some of the traps of a game a
system
given that would you describe unity 2020
as a game b
project it's certainly an attempt to
create a a game b
project in political space it is
obviously
built to defeat the duopoly
on the duopoly's home turf so almost by
definition this is a game b
whether or not it can succeed and
whether it is long-term stable
is harder to tell i would say
one thing that is very clear from the
inside of the unity movement
is just how much the duopoly is
depending on its ability to bar
competitors from the landscape as you
point out in your introduction to unity
the major parties have delivered us
offerings that are
absolutely preposterous and would seem
to leave
those parties open to challenge from
anybody who could muster
a better ticket but the obstacles to
doing so
are absolutely ferocious
and that is the question can something
like unity that is structurally built to
defeat the arguments that prevent
uh anything from outside of the duopoly
from functioning
is that new structure sufficient
to break in could you summarize what you
think of the game b
dynamics and the game a dynamic that
this is kind of
designed to deal with
sure the first thing i would say is that
this election in the u.s is revealing
that the key feature that allows
the major parties to survive is their
ability to bar
entry to anything that has the capacity
to challenge them
so on the democratic side in particular
we're seeing
a party that refuses to articulate
any positive vision refuses to advance
candidates that catalyze the imagination
and is running entirely on the argument
that it is the only reasonable vote
in light of the opposition so
that is not a strong position
electorally
it is in fact very easy to come up with
candidates who do catalyze the
imagination to come up with policies
that are popular to come up with
strategies that are more
nimble what is impossible to do is to
get a seat at the table
which would allow you to compete head to
head with the feeble
offerings of the major parties so
first and foremost unity is a project
that attacks the primary
obstacle to what are typically described
as third-party offerings now unity is
not a party but nonetheless it runs up
against the bulwark
that is designed to prevent other
parties from challenging the duopoly
and that that primary weapon is the
argument
that if your values are over here and
you marshal a third party that's over
here you will rob
the major party that's closer to your
values and empower the one that's
farther away so what you do will be
counterproductive
because you will elect the greater evil
the key
dynamic inside of the unity proposal is
that we take
a uh a draft e from the left and a draft
e
from the right and we bring them
together under an agreement
that they would rule by consensus and so
you can't
place unity on the political spectrum
because it's apolitical
it's not ideological and because of that
the argument that you will empower the
greater evil by deploying this strategy
and therefore are morally required not
to deploy it that argument falls flat
for anybody who's tracking the analytics
now interestingly
although the analytics fail many people
are emotionally
so wrapped up in the idea that somehow
this will spoil an election that they
won't even allow themselves to
contemplate the idea
so they have been traumatized by the
major parties they've watched people
like ralph nader and jill stein be
demonized
as the spoilers that elected the greater
evil and they don't want responsibility
so even though it is irrational to fear
unity on this basis people still do at
least some of them
so just to kind of outline it it's two
candidates
uh ideally one from the right one from
the left who who are kind of
in joint making joint decisions through
consensus
how is that consensus enforced
wouldn't the president because once they
if they win
there's a coin toss and then the
president is chosen that way how how do
you avoid
the fact that the situation that the
president just has the kind of veto
power over those decisions
um well i would say first of all let me
just correct one thing they're not
candidates
what we have are potential draftees
this is phrased uh as a draft very
intentionally
because one of the things that we needed
to accomplish was
that the offerings had to not be limited
to those people who were
let's say independent of the bulwark
created by the duopoly
that is to say the best candidates had
to be chosen from the full
menu and that meant
that we couldn't seek their uh we
couldn't ask them to
run in advance of choosing who we
ideally wanted to draft
so in essence what we did was we ran
a poll to figure out who ideally we
wanted to see inhabit the office
and our hope was that having been drawn
from right and left
the constituency of unity which voted on
who we wish to draft
would choose people with the capacity to
work across
a political divide and the instinct to
do it
and we didn't know if it would work but
what we discovered was that it did
we got six people were
nominated for our draft and
three came from the left three came from
the right we then ran
a ranked choice vote to see which
ordering people preferred these tickets
in the top choice
turned out to be tulsi gabbard and dan
crenshaw
now it turns out tulsi gabbard and dan
crenshaw are friends
they are from opposite parties they
quite like each other and have no
trouble
working productively together so the
answer to your question
is that our guess at what one would have
to do
in order to find the ability to reach
consensus
worked beautifully and we couldn't be
happier
um that this ticket is the one that rose
to the top
have have they agreed to to be part of
it
uh no and in fact i would counsel them
not to agree
the fact is these are the best people we
have
in our system and because we are
patriotic americans we want them strong
irrespective of whether or not
this is in a unity context or in their
present context
so the the nature of the draft is that
we have to deliver
them something that
would justify they're taking the risk of
partnering with us
and that has not happened yet but our
hope is that it will
over the coming weeks i i've been
thinking about a kind of a good
definition of game a and game b and one
of the
i think one of the most compelling
visions of that is the the series the
wire
you familiar with that the the david
simon
series it is my favorite piece of
television ever
what i love about that is that it
demonstrates
that almost all of these power systems
create these compromises create these
kind of boxed in
uh situations whether you're part of the
police force or whether you're part of a
drug gang
you are no not free because of the the
nature of those systems
i think that's an excellent analysis and
by going through
one area after another
doing this by season it highlighted the
fact that it was basically the game
theory ruling each of these
uh each of these dynamics so yeah it's a
perfect analogy
if we use that as a kind of definition
of game a for me it's a perfect example
and it
it uses game theory to explain why
you'll know
you're not free for all of these
different reasons within these different
systems
um for for me it's interesting to look
at the situation that we're in
and in some ways trump did break the
duopoly
he came as an outsider from outside the
republican party
and would you would you agree with that
and i
i think it's really interesting to look
at trump as
for me a kind of herald at the end of
game a
like he seems to be a product of the end
of game a he's kind of
like a zero trust environment he's kind
of the prisoner's dilemma made flesh
for me as a kind of in a game theoretic
sense it's like if
if you devote yourself to anything
bigger than you yourself you're a sucker
as we saw recently with the with the
comments about the
the kind of the armed forces like he
just doesn't get the idea of anything
bigger than himself
which i'd like to follow this thread a
little bit what would you what would you
say to that
first of all i would say he absolutely
was a successful challenge to the
duopoly
he decapitated the gop and so one of the
reasons that
um explaining where we are is difficult
is that we are challenging the duopoly
but the duopoly has already
been reformed by trump who demonstrated
that it was possible
so unfortunately for the reasons you
just outlined
it was not a highly useful demonstration
in the sense of what followed the
payload of what was carried in
in place of the previous power structure
has been well maybe it's even generous
to say
a mixed bag but the
proof of concept that it is possible
was very powerful and you know i think
what we saw in 2016 was a
real challenge to both sides of the
duopoly
in the form of bernie sanders on the
left and donald trump on the right
now bernie sanders almost made it but
his constraints were greater
as you point out bernie sanders well you
don't point this out about bernie but
you point out
trump doesn't have obligation to things
larger than himself and
that frees him maximally to do whatever
is necessary
to move forward bernie sanders is
committed to certain moral principles
and as such
in the end he fell on his sword you know
what i think is a mistaken attempt to
to adhere to those principles but
nonetheless
the democratic side of the duopoly has
been more successful at preventing
insurgents from breaking its
stranglehold leading to the absolutely
absurd
2020 situation of
two candidates neither of which inspire
anyone with no proposal about how to
make things
better and one of them clearly
evidencing signs of
cognitive failure i mean if you wrote
this as a script people wouldn't buy it
it's not even plausible and yet here we
are
and what's your concern if trump wins
then
i have tremendous concerns if trump wins
for one thing
the what we have unfolding in the u.s
and really i think in the west
at a larger scale is a competition
between two narratives both of which are
wrong and the unrest in
the american streets is predicated on
the idea that
white supremacy is rampant and
riddled throughout our system that it
hides behind every corner that it is
in every white mind that's obvious
nonsense but
the fact of that accusation now being
leveled
and with quite a bit of stigmatizing
power
level leveled against anybody who
resists it this is going to drive
white people together it's going to
drive the very racism
that is claimed to exist already
and that racism will find
safe harbor in a
uh trumpian gop
milieu where it hasn't been at home in
some time
the way that the media frames trump sort
of seems to be as kind of
orange hitler like he's got some kind of
big authoritarian plan
i think people sense
that that's not probably not true
because trump doesn't have any kind of a
plan
but my concern is that the nature of
trump's psychology
could lead him in that direction through
pure naked self-interest
and because there's a tremendous
opportunity that will be generated by
the lunacy
on the left a couple of years ago i put
out a video
i think the title of it was speak of the
devil and it was about this very process
where in leveling false
accusations about the degree of white
supremacy for example
in the u.s that the
foolishness on the democratic side
would cause people on the republican
side to begin to view the world in
exactly those terms and it would create
a revival of
white racism in the u.s that has been
close to flickering out for several
decades now
so i have this fear exactly that a
an opportunist like trump
will find himself behaving in exactly
the way
that he has been accused of planning and
clearly wasn't planning we're now almost
four years into
the trump presidency and uh it hasn't
been a case of the rise of a new hitler
and the left has
not admitted this which it really it's
about time that it did
and it also points to something i think
that
certainly eric has talked about and
perhaps you've talked about as well is
that
the sense of all of the opportunity
being hoarded by a certain generation i
mean you look at now
everyone was born in the 1940s it's
basically the baby baby boomer
generation refusing to give up power
what do you make of that dynamic
well i think eric has been right to
point out even just at the level of
noticing the pattern
the shocking concentration of
wealth and power in this now dwindling
generation i think it's part of a larger
dynamic though
essentially what we have is a system
that has
through an evolutionary process turned
into one
that amplifies and perpetuates existing
distributions of well-being
and so what really has happened i think
is not that
the boomers have conspired against
the future it's that anything that is
powerful has been
given um impressive tools with which
to not uh pass the torch
and that works racially that works
generationally it works uh at all kinds
of levels
and the fact of these
two geriatric candidates running is a
manifestation of that larger process
and what do you make i remember on a
on a recent live stream with heather you
both talked about how
um you were equally that there was sort
of trump
trump delusion syndrome often on the
left but there was an equivalent
on on the right where some people just
wouldn't hear criticism of him
and you were equally kind of uh
concerned about both
i i wonder i mean as i look at the the
election the way i look at it with
i just can't see if trump is the the
sort of
the herald at the end of game a like
he's the kind of the
the ultimate boss of that kind of
dysfunctional way of doing things
i i just don't see aesthetically
from a sort of storyline perspective it
just doesn't make any sense that we're
going to go back to an obama-era
democrat it's just like i just can't see
it happening
i mean i don't i don't know what the
next stage is but
it doesn't look good for all sorts of
different reasons and it just seems
it just seems almost impossible that it
it could be a abide in victory
just from a sort of sense of the story
arc of where we've been and where we're
going
i i absolutely agree with this i mean i
believe we are staring
at the collapse of the democratic party
the democratic party has effectively
announced that there's nothing left in
the tank and
i don't know why anybody is imagining
that an entity that performed this badly
in terms of nominating candidates to
defeat what they claim is
you know this historic evil right the
fact that it would
that it would advance such a feeble
ticket is
proof positive that it has no idea where
to go
and i think the way it is handling the
unrest in the u.s
is equally strong evidence this is a
recipe for electoral disaster
they're going to lose to trump if
something like unity does not swoop in
and allow something reasonable to happen
and from my perspective it is
frustrating to see people conclude
that the democrats are right there
in the hunt i think on the basis that
they typically always are
and i think people are just failing to
look at the evidence in front of them
well you could argue i mean they are
ahead in the polls
and have been quite substantially for a
while
um i don't know why anyone finds that
comforting in light of 2016.
what we know is that there is incredible
pressure
for people not to say that they are
considering voting for donald trump and
that when they end up
voting many of the people who swear
they're not going to do that do
anyway and their reason to do it in this
circumstance
is becoming more
rational in light of the threat posed to
average americans by unrest in the
streets
the fact is the democrats have
effectively announced
a an unwillingness to address this
problem
it really is threatening people in their
homes and
that is going to result in people voting
for the one thing
that they think might protect them so
a loss for the democrats is perfectly
predictable here
and in light of that loss given what
people on the left believe
about trump you would imagine that this
would make them receptive to anybody who
was offering something coherent
in his stead and yet there is this
i would argue sheepish tendency to
simply imagine that what has been
is what will be and we know that that's
you know
that's rule of thumb at best and history
doesn't work that way
new things happen and they take over and
trump was one and sanders was
one and here we are in 2020
staring at an absolutely unprecedented
competition between two tickets that
don't look like anything that has
preceded them so
something unprecedented is about to
happen and the fact that
people imagine that unprecedented thing
will be as precedented as possible
is uh it's a failure of imagination
and there have been a few um
practical criticisms of the the unity
plan like about ballot access in
particular
that it was launched very uh too late to
get people onto the ballot
well we we wouldn't have been proceeding
with this if there wasn't a mechanism
for doing it
and this again shows that uh
people are
overly obligated to their models of how
things are done
and the fact is the duopoly has blocked
every normal mode that you might use to
challenge them so by definition any
successful challenge will have to be
abnormal
now what people expect is oh if you're
going to get on the ballot what you do
is you collect
huge numbers of signatures you have to
do so in every state
and that that is you know it requires a
gigantic
effort just to gain viability on the
other hand
we have numerous parties that are not
in and of themselves viable we have two
major ones and many minor ones
and they have ballot access which they
are free to allocate
and so in a moment where americans are
actually
fleeing cities that they live in moving
to places that they
feel that violence is less likely to
reach them
that's an emergency moment and the
question is can
these third parties that have ballot
access recognize
that not only is it the patriotic thing
to do
to join together under a unity banner
and
do something that might electorally
succeed but it is also in their interest
to do it
that the duopoly is their enemy and
defeating it is in their interest
you know in general ways but also very
specific ones
any party that gains five percent in the
election
gets federal funds in the next cycle
that's a very substantial advantage that
they would have
it's also true that unity has already
displayed a commitment to rank choice
voting which is a mechanism that would
greatly enhance the power of third
parties
to bring coherence to our national
discussion
so joining with unity makes a good deal
of sense for
any third party and there are numerous
ways it could happen the simplest
way would be for the greens or
libertarians to see the wisdom in this
plan
and to to join with us but there are
many other parties
and it's there there are many paths to
the ballot
in all 50 states when you first pitched
the
the plan the unity plan you mentioned
the two names that came to mind at first
were andrew yang and william mcraven
and that seemed to make quite a lot of
sense in terms of
uh a military figure coming in i think
he was a university president before
uh chancellor of the university of texas
yeah so he's sort of coming from
slightly outside politics and and coming
in
that seemed to make a lot of sense
when the when the choice shifted to to
tulsi
and dan crenshaw for me that seemed to
make less sense because they are
political figures they're within the
the the parties and i i would argue a
sort of subject to the same kind of game
a forces that
that everyone else is subject to
crenshaw has to is thinking about a run
potentially in 2024
there are he he's kind of in that in
that game
like i i have to say i was it it changed
the nature of it for me when
when those when those names were
announced
well i understand that i have to say i
think uh
we have already demonstrated something
very powerful
with unity 2020 and we demonstrated it
by running
a completely
[Music]
how can i put it a completely
successful mechanized attempt to count
the will of our constituents
and put it into action
i take that back that was not well said
i have to figure out some better way of
saying it
okay
the unity movement is composed
of a great many volunteers who are
engaged in the process of making it
happen and a much larger group
of people who are paying attention to
the movement and interested in
what it does and in running this vote
we did not meddle with the will of our
constituents so
what happened was they had the ability
to nominate potential draftees and then
to vote on them and the only thing we
did was eliminate people we didn't
think met the unity criteria
so what happened was tulsi gabbard and
dan crenshaw rose to the top
in a perfectly natural process and i
must say i am
quite pleased with the ticket i find the
fact that these figures genuinely are
from two different sides of the
political spectrum
that they have genuine respect for each
other each one has displayed
a great deal of courage and patriotism
and the
the pairing of them does seem to create
a natural balance
as for them being too much within the
system
i would say i personally have had
several interactions now
with dan crenshaw and although he and i
are on very different
parts of the political spectrum we have
no trouble
finding common ground and seeing the
humanity in each other so i believe
the individual is quite up to the
challenge and
um in tulsi's case she has faced
absolutely um diabolical challenges from
her
own party the worst of which being
hillary clinton's
alleging that she was a russian asset
during
the primaries so this team
is one that has awareness of just how
toxic these parties can be
and has an instinct to to act in the
nation's interest
irrespective of what the parties think
and i'm very happy with the ticket
would i have been happy with yang and
mcraven
i would have been the reason i named
them when i first unveiled the proposal
was that i thought highly of them both
and i saw that they had the potential to
do the same thing
but gabbard and crenshaw seems to me
a perfectly viable unity ticket
and what's more when one compares it to
the offerings that the major parties
have provided
there's simply no contest i don't want
to concentrate or stay
too long on either of the figures
because that's not the point of the
conversation but
um crenshaw for example
and i'm just i'm just taking his his um
actions here he posted on facebook a
while ago that trump was an idiot
his rhetoric was insane and hateful and
has then
flipped round to actually being one of
trump's most kind of ardent defenders
like for me that illustrates the problem
with the game a system
i'm not i'm not making that a comment
about him specifically
but the the forces are pushing someone
like crenshaw has got a political
ambition to run in 2024
towards supporting someone who he
probably actually does not
uh align with on many levels like
it just seems to be a much bigger game
theoretic trap
than than any of us than than is able to
be dealt with by this plan
on the contrary um the fact is yes
dan crenshaw has said some things that
uh
don't fit with what i think a completely
free actor
would say given what i am certain he
believes
that is to say he's a smart guy and he
is playing a political game because
that's the system he's in but
i would say one of the things back in
the uh the days when game b was first
being
formulated i did a lot of thinking about
what game a is composed of
and there are three kinds of actors in
our system
there are those who will do the right
thing no matter what
these people are not powerful because
they
they are too obligated to principle to
be successful and although
i admire them we don't see them very
frequently
inside of the system we have people who
will do
what is in their self-interest no matter
what
at any cost to others we see a fair
number of those
and then we have people who are
reluctant participants in game a
who given a game b option would take it
and so if we're going to judge all of
the people in the system who are
successfully
playing the game a game if we're going
to judge them
for having touched game a then all hope
is lost
if we are going to provide a better
option and then
allow them to jump ship from game a into
something that aspires
to a much better outcome on game
theoretically sound basis then there's a
lot of hope and so
i am quite confident having interacted
with dan crenshaw
that although he's a very successful
game a player
that given a better game he'd be glad to
play that one
and he would do very well in it i think
his instincts are the right ones
i'm not going to fault him for
playing a strategically wise game inside
of washington
because frankly that's what has him
there and i'm glad that he's in the room
because i know that his instinct is to
protect the nation and we need it
and in those three categories you just
laid out
how would you describe yourself because
the the
the story of evergreen would suggest
that you were someone who would kind of
say what he believed no matter what do
you do you see yourself as someone who
occasionally collaborates occasionally
stands up or you which category put
yourself
well what i would point out is that
first of all
whether i have gotten somewhere or not
gotten somewhere
is dependent on which metric you use
game a does a tremendous job of ignoring
the world of podcasters let's say
right it did a very poor job handling
the evergreen story what made the
evergreen
story resonate for people were outsiders
who didn't even have a seat at the table
in game a
you know mike nena's documentary shocked
people
it was brilliantly done but mike nena is
not
with a major outfit he's a freelancer
from australia
born in mauritius right this is um
a very different kind of player so to
the extent that game b
is rising on the outskirts of game a
i've done alright and i don't think
that's surprising you would expect
a game b player to play
well in game b and as i've pointed out
elsewhere game a and game b
are always in competition now it happens
that game a
has been so dominant for so long that we
view it as the entirety of things but
there's always
um limited venues in which game b
shines and i would say those limited
venues are becoming
more public because of the fragility of
game a which is finally showing
so yes i have succeeded but i don't
think i've succeeded in the sense
that i'm winning within game a i'm
winning on the outskirts of game a
at best over in a place where game b
values are held and i don't think that
should surprise anyone
i'd like to bring in a couple more
topics that i've been thinking about a
lot and i know that you've been thinking
about as well
and um issues that affect all of us who
are kind of operating in this kind of
alternative sense-making space
i saw a live stream with you and heather
a while ago where it's mostly heather
talking about
how you the the algorithms had been
categorizing your content in a certain
way
and this sense of being um
i i'd say that that you you want to
appear or you want to to present a
perspective that's kind of nuanced and
is not right and is not left
but you were being kind of drawn towards
one side of the spectrum
rather than the other where do you think
you've ended up and
what do you think the dangers are of of
the kind of algorithmic
manipulation of this space
well let's be very clear in
in being drawn somewhere this is really
a matter of
the portrayal that the algorithm
portrays you as one way or the other
based on
the incentives of the corporations that
are deploying these algorithms
i think we have been very successful at
resisting
the temptation to feed the audience
that is finding our content that is to
say
there were years where people
who were arriving at our doorstep
were typically right of center and there
was a lot of insistence that we were
being
so-called red pilled and that we would
wake up to
the conservative reality of the world
and that would
complete the story and the fact is we
haven't moved to the right
even though um there was a niche for us
to do so there would it would have been
financially rewarding for example to
acknowledge the truth of conservatism
and be heralded on that side but instead
the
the honest thing to do was to say that
actually this story isn't
a clear victory for conservatism even if
reason
is finding safe harbor on the
conservative side at the moment
but you can't beat the algorithm for one
thing
you can't see it and for another thing
it's not stable the algorithm is
changing it's a moving target so even if
your detectors
were
unusually capable of figuring out what
the algorithm was doing and in some way
correcting for its effect
the fact that it changes over time makes
that job impossible so
we are in in some sense enslaved to
its view of the world and what it does
among
presumably many things is it feeds
people things
that they either want to hear or that
will enrage them enough to keep them
focused
and both of those processes are
absolutely toxic
to sense making sense making requires
doesn't require that you have perfect
access to the world but it does require
a a relatively
useful signal-to-noise ratio that allows
you to detect the signal
and to process it and the problem is
there is
signal in the distortion that the
algorithm introduces its signal about
what
google for example wants the fact that
the algorithms
are serving the economic and possibly
political interests
of those who are deploying them is
absolutely toxic to sense making
it does not allow you to view the world
it's like
we've purchased glasses from somebody
that wants us to see
certain things and not see other things
and we have to take the glasses off but
our means for doing that
is essentially non-existent because we
don't know
what the glasses are doing which
distortions they are introducing and
when
it is impossible to correct for them and
i believe that this is actually creating
a literal derangement of civilization
that what we are seeing in the streets
for example
is effectively a group psychosis
that is born of an incorrect
understanding of
events and if left to
continue this trajectory will be
utterly devastating to western
civilization
and possibly beyond and i think that
comes back to the nature of the filter
bubble and to the nature of the
algorithms
so basically if you're a black lives
matter supporter your
your facebook feed which is just an
infinite scroll
of stuff that is designed to push your
buttons looks completely different from
a trump supporters
facebook feed and there just seems like
there is there are no
there are now no places where those two
worlds overlap
and that is just increasingly kind of
leaking out into the
into the real world well i wouldn't say
no places i think there are islands and
i think
rebel wisdom is one such island i think
dark horse podcast and the portal
are other islands but i know that
personally
i seek out both narratives
and i compare them and i'm sure that i
am not doing a perfect job of seeing
them but i'm doing
enough of a job that i understand that
i'm being
lied to in two different directions and
that does not lead to a whole lot of
certainty about exactly what is going on
but it does lead to proper skepticism of
what we are told is going on
something that has changed since we last
spoke is
we've seen what looks like and i covered
it in the sense making series
matt taibi in particular sort of
said a bit of a mia culpa uh obviously
this was much worse than we realized we
were kind of silent on this
you've also had glenn greenwald starting
to to speak out on it
both sort of stalwarts of the left mata
iglesias also kind of
raising concerns do you see those
those sort of signs of hope as
potentially quite important like for me
it does feel like there's there's
beginning to be a bit of a change
within the left especially around the
people starting to spot that there is a
danger of this sort of ideological
um framework that's been nurtured on the
left
there's certainly a degree of hope in it
i'm pleased to see people
waking up but i'm also frustrated
because
the key thing about recognizing that you
had it wrong
is figuring out why you had it wrong so
that you don't get it wrong the next
time
and there are some people that i think
are doing this job
as well as possible matt tybee would be
a great example
and then there are others who just want
now that
they have figured out that they had it
wrong they just want to simply inhabit
the right position
and now they're the new experts and the
point is nope
you actually blew it and the discovery
that you blew it
now means you need to study the process
that misled you
so that you understand what that error
was made of
and in the case of for example
mataglasius
i don't see that i don't see the self
skepticism that should have been caused
by the discovery that he had it wrong so
it's a mixed bag and i hope we can get
to this process because ultimately the
cost of having been
wrong in this case is gargantuan
yeah i mean it does seem to me just from
the last
three months or so that there has been a
change i mean the harper's letter
was also i know i think i think you you
may have a slightly different take on
that but for me it was a
it was a line it was a sort of very
tenuous line in the sand but the
response to it
showed the problem and you did have a
huge number of people signing that
letter
and i think the response in the
aftermath showed the issue you can argue
with the wording of the letter and i
think you would have worded it
differently
but for me it was strong enough for
people to get behind
and then the aftermath really
demonstrated what the issue
was i i saw you discuss it and said that
you wouldn't have signed it
do you look at it differently at all now
no i think the letter evidence is
exactly
the matti iglesias problem which is that
people who got it wrong are now looking
to carve out a new deal
that protects them rather than recognize
that they put
a lot of us in jeopardy and that that
jeopardy is their responsibility
and it's not that everyone who signed
the letter is in that boat
my biggest concern about the letter was
that it dragged people who have been
very far-sighted
on this question like jonathan height
in with people like maddie iglesias and
then it excluded others
so those who had this right
should be the ones pointing the
direction to go so we don't make the
mistake again
rather than grouping people who are
still understood to be part of polite
society
and excluding those who were demonized
by them
so the idw for example was portrayed as
some sort of
far right alt-right this that or the
other
that portrayal was absolute nonsense and
that stigma is still in force that
stigma is the reason
that no one from idw was invited to sign
that letter
just returning to the
um the unity 2020 plan it relies
on a groundswell of support you've made
that clear
at what point do you need that
groundswell of support to happen
and when at what point will you
decide whether it has or hasn't
uh it needs to happen very soon now
there's a question
we have a lot of things which might if
one of the things that we need were to
fall into place
it would catalyze the others and so
there's sort of a question of uh
what is the first cause here but yes it
has to happen very soon in order for it
to be a plausible plan
i won't say more than that because the
details of exactly when depend
on how events unfold and they also
depend
on the decisions of individual states
with respect to their ballots
and could could you talk more about what
those things are that you think might
catalyze that process
i can't because they're in motion and i
don't my
primary objective is to give this plan
the maximum chance of
functioning in the 2020 cycle and
discussing
the exact details of how it might unfold
and what is in motion
is clearly a hazard to the plan so
in the interests of unity 2020 i'm going
to
leave it at that our ability to make
sense of the world
is breaking down we're making more and
more consequential choices
with worse and worse sense making to
inform those choices
which is kind of running increasingly
fast
through the woods increasingly blind
over the last two years rebel wisdom has
interviewed some of the world's top
thinkers
now we've brought them together for an
eight-week online course
sensemaking 101 with daniel
schmacktenberger
diane mucho hamilton john viveki
doshin roshi and more improve your sense
making
develop your sovereignty and join a
wider community
looking to do the same